Inventory of the Willbur Fisk Papers: Correspondence from Willbur Fisk (Chronological), 1812 - 1839
Willbur Fisk Papers: Correspondence from Wilbur Fisk (Chronological), 1812 - 1839
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Fisk, Willbur.
1000-91
1.0
2
Willbur Fisk (1792-1839) was a Methodist minister and the first president of Wesleyan University.
Correspondence from Willbur Fisk (Chronological) contains a complete chronological list of the letters from Willbur Fisk. For the complete finding aid to the Willbur Fisk Papers, visit http://www.wesleyan.edu/libr/schome/FAs/fi1000-91.html.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Materials collected by the college library in the 19th century.
Biographical Note
Willbur Fisk, Wesleyan’s first president, was born on 31 August 1792 and grew up in Brattleboro, Vermont. Although his mother feared that godlessness and sin in schools and colleges would make Fisk too worldly and strangle the spiritual life, Fisk graduated from Brown University in 1815, after also attending Peacham Academy and the University of Vermont. Surprisingly, given his future role at Wesleyan, Fisk was not initially drawn to the Methodist ministry following school. In fact, he struggled with his spiritual purpose at that time, working in law and as a tutor. However, a revelation during a bout of illness brought him to the ministry in 1818, and he devoted the rest of his life to his work as a Methodist. In 1825, Fisk was appointed principal of Wesleyan Academy in Wilbraham, Massachusetts, a preparatory school from which many Wesleyan University students were to be drawn.
When the decision to found a university in Middletown, Connecticut was made, Fisk was tapped for the role of first president. In his inaugural speech in 1831, he outlined his vision for the university, encapsulated by the statement that Education should be directed in reference to two objects—the good of the individual educated and the good of the world. Fisk was deeply involved in the administrative and curricular decisions of Wesleyan, and raised funds for the new college. He traveled to Europe to study educational institutions and collect scientific equipment in 1835-1836, and also took that time as a break from the stresses of the presidency. Suffering from ill-health his entire life, Fisk finally succumbed on 22 February 1839 while still serving as president.
Collection Overview
Correspondence from Willbur Fisk contains letters sent by Fisk to others, arranged in chronological order. For the complete finding aid to the Willbur Fisk Papers, visit http://www.wesleyan.edu/libr/schome/FAs/fi1000-91.html.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Correspondence from Willbur Fisk (Chronological)
  For the complete finding aid to the Willbur Fisk Papers, visit http://www.wesleyan.edu/libr/schome/FAs/fi1000-91.html.
  - 1812 (Box 7)
    - 8 November 1812: Phinehas Peck
  - 1813
    - 16 May 1813: Mary Fisk
    - 30 May 1813: Marcia Palmer
  - 1814
    - 11 June 1814: Mary Fisk
    - 23 July 1814: Mary Fisk
    - 9 August 1814: Franklin Deming
    - 15 August 1814: Mary Fisk
    - 14 October 1814: Mary Fisk
    - 30 November 1814: Mary Fisk
  - 1815
    - 17 January 1815: B. Franklin Deming
    - 23 April 1815: Mary Fisk
    - 14 July 1815: B. Franklin Deming
  - 1816
    - 19 April 1816: Marcia Palmer
    - 13 May 1816: David Gould
    - 15 May 1815: Marcy Palmer
    - 18 June 1816: Isaiah Fisk
    - 29 June 1816: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 10 August 1816: Isaiah Fisk
    - 10 August 1816: Marcia Palmer
    - 16 August 1816: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 26 August 1816: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 26 October 1816: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 2 November 1816: Marcia Palmer
    - 23 November 1816: Isaiah Fisk
    - 23 December 1816: Ruth Peck
  - 1817
    - 18 January 1817: Phinehas Peck
    - 1 February 1817: B. F. Deming
    - 5 February 1817: Phinehas Peck
    - 11 February 1817: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 3 March 1817: Mary Fisk
    - 15 March 1817: David Gould
    - 26 March 1817: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 26 March 1817: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 3 May 1817: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 2 June 1817: Isaiah Fisk
    - 16 July 1817: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 9 September 1817: Marcia Palmer
    - 13 September 1817: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 27 October 1817: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
  - 1818
    - 8 January 1818: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 6 February 1818: Marcy Palmer
    - 12 February 1818: G. Cahoon
    - 26 March 1818: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 29 April 1818: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 23 May 1818: B. F. Deming
    - 13 June 1818: Harvey Scott
    - 23 July 1818: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 16 August 1818: Phinehas Peck
    - 26 September 1818: Harvey Scott
    - 29 September 1818: Benjamin R. Hoyt
    - 29 October 1818: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
  - 1819
    - 11 February 1819: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 11 February 1819: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 5 March 1819: Mary Fisk
    - 22 April 1819: George Taft
    - 23 April 1819: Mary Fisk
    - 15 July 1819: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 2 August 1819: Isaiah Fisk
    - 27 September 1819: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 20 November 1819: Mary Fisk
    - 1 December 1819: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 1 December 1819: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
  - 1820
    - 15 February 1820: Isaiah Fisk
    - 21 February 1820: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 20 March 1820: Marcy Palmer
    - 20 March 1829: Mary Fisk
    - 26 March 1820: Prof. Holdich
    - 2 May 1820: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 23 May 1820: unknown
    - 30 June 1820: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 18 August 1820: Daniel Filmore
    - 18 September 1820: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 18 September 1820: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 25 October 1820: Mary Fisk
    - 25 October 1820: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 16 December 1820: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
  - 1821
    - 24 January 1821: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 15 February 1821: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 3 March 1821: Mary Fisk
    - 20 March 1821: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 6 April 1821: Mary Fisk
    - 27 April 1821: Unknown
    - 30 June 1821: Marcy Palmer
    - 6 August 1821: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 6 August 1821: Unknown
    - 10 October 1821: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 30 October 1821: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 17 November 1821: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 20 November 1821: Rufus Barrus
  - 1822
    - 9 January 1822: Phinehas Peck
    - 25 January 1822: Unknown
    - 6 February 1822: Maria and Rebecca Osborn
    - 6 May 1822: Daniel Filmore
    - 13 July 1822: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 8 August 1822: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 16 August 1822: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 15 October 1822: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 27 October 1822: Daniel Filmore
    - 10 December 1822: Marcy Palmer
  - 1823
    - 15 January 1823: Daniel Filmore
    - 21 February 1823: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 21 February 1823: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 28 April 1823: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 30 April 1823: Mary Phipps
    - 8 May 1823: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 7 July 1823: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 4 August 1823: Daniel Filmore
    - 13 August 1823: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 5 September 1823: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 16 October 1823: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 17 December 1823: John Lyndsey
  - 1824
    - 26 April 1824: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 22 May 1824: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 26 May 1824: Benj. F. Deming
    - 26 July 1824: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 15 November 1824: John Lindsey
  - 1825
    - 26 July 1825: Marcy Palmer
  - 1827
    - 20 March 1827: John Lindsey
    - 2 April 1827: Marcy Palmer
    - 1 September 1827: Samuel Luckey
    - 20 November 1827: Mr. Canfield
    - 7 December 1827: N. Bangs and J. Emory
  - 1828
    - 2 February 1828: John Lindsey
    - 14 March 1828: Mr. Eddy
    - 24 March 1828: Marcia Knowlton
    - 21 April 1828: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 29 April 1828: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 8 May 1828: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 9 May 1828: Bishop Love
    - 17 May 1828: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 24 May 1828: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 25 June 1828: Mary Fisk Allton
    - 3 September 1828: Hannah Fisk
    - 6 November 1828: P. P. Sandford
    - 23 November 1828: Marcy Palmer
    - 4 December 1828: Henry Archibald
    - 4 December 1828: John Foster
    - 17 December 1828: Samuel Luckey
  - 1829
    - 6 February 1829: John Peterson
    - 23 February 1829: Daniel Brayton
    - 5 March 1829: Benj. Jones
    - 7 March 1829: Seth Lathrop
    - 30 March 1829: Egerton Ryerson
    - 6 April 1829: Austin Dickinson
    - 15 April 1829: A Clergyman
    - 31 July 1829: J. F. Adams
    - 12 September 1829: Rev. Laban Clark
    - 20 September 1829: N. Bangs
    - 23 September 1829: Isaiah Fisk
    - 1 November 1829: Daniel Brayton
  - 1830
    - 7 February 1830: Orange Scott
    - 27 February 1830: Rev. Laban Clark
    - 2 April 1830: William Clark
    - 24 April 1830: William Clark
    - 16 May 1830: Marcia Knowlton
    - 4 June 1830: To Families at Wilbraham
    - 12 June 1830: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 26 August 1830: To the Joint Board of Trustees and Visitors of the Wesleyan University
      Letter of acceptance of the Presidency of the University.
    - 29 August 1830: Charles K. True
    - 20 September 1830: Mary Fisk Allton
    - 8 October 1830: John Lindsey
    - 22 December 1830: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 31 December 1830: Marcia Knowlton
  - 1831
    - 1831: A. W. Smith
    - 14 January 1831: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 15 May 1831: Unknown
    - 10 August 1831: Susan Brewer
    - 28 October 1831: Unknown
    - 16 December 1831: Joseph Holdich
    - 29 December 1831: Augustus W. Smith
  - 1832
    - 5 January 1832: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 27 January 1832: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 2 February 1832: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 3 March 1832: Isaiah Fisk
    - 19 March 1832: Marcy Palmer
    - 5 May 1832: Augustus W. Smith
    - 12 May 1832: Augustus W. Smith
    - 11 June 1832: Mary Fisk Allton
    - 10 July 1832: Augustus W. Smith
    - 13 September 1832: Oren Allton
    - 20 October 1832: Isaiah Fisk
  - 1833
    - 1833: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 3 January 1833: Hannah Fisk
    - 3 January 1833: Marcy Palmer
    - 12 January 1833: Samuel Luckey
    - 24 January 1833: Daniel D. Whedon
    - 22 March 1833: Marcia Knowlton
      In two parts.
    - 5 June 1833: Ruth P. Fisk
    - 24 June 1833: Charles L. Brown
    - 3 August 1833: Charles K. True
    - 28 September 1833: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 25 October 1833: Ira M. Bidwell
    - 7 November 1833: Benj. F. Deming
    - 4 December 1833: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
  - 1834
    - 7 February 1834: Marcy Palmer
    - 15 March 1834: Benj. F. Deming
    - 2 April 1834: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 25 April 1834: Benj. F. Deming
    - 26 April 1834: E. Jackson
    - 26 April 1834: Spencer Mattison
    - 15 May 1834: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 19 June 1834: Christian Keener
    - 23 July 1834: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 6 August 1834: Eunice Deming
    - 6 August 1834: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 1 November 1834: Marcy Palmer
    - 4 November 1834: J. Bunting, D. D.
    - 23 November 1834: Isaiah Fisk
    - November 1834: Dr. Nathan Bangs
    - 2 December 1834: Dr. Nathan Bangs
    - 30 December 1834: Dr. Nathan Bangs
  - 1835
    - 12 January 1835: George Round
    - 25 January 1835: Isaiah Fisk
    - 10 March 1835: Hezekiah L. Ramsdell
    - 21 March 1835: Marcy Palmer
    - 30 June 1835: LeRoy Sunderland
    - July 1835: Augustus W. Smith
    - 6 July 1835: Charles K. True
    - 29 July 1835: LeRoy Sunderland
    - 4 August 1835: John Johnstone
    - 1 September 1835: Marcy Palmer
    - 7 September 1835: Lydia Peck
    - 8 September 1835: Lydia Peck
    - 26 September 1835: Lydia Peck
    - 30 September 1835: Augustus W. Smith (Box 7)
    - 30 October 1835: Lydia Peck
    - 5 November 1835: Augustus W. Smith
    - 21 November 1835: Rev. Laban Clark
      Sent from Paris.
  - 1836
    - 1836: Samuel Luckey
    - 12 February 1836: Dr. Bunting
    - 14 February 1836: Martha S. Fisk
    - 29 February 1836: Unknown
    - 2 March 1836: Harvey B. Lane
    - 9 March 1836: Lydia Peck
    - 24 April 1836: Isaiah Fisk
    - 1 May 1836: Mary Hurlbut
    - 8 May 1836: Unknown
    - 21 May 1836: John Johnstone
    - 6 October 1836: Augustus W. Smith
    - November 1836: Unknown
    - 23 November 1836: Isaiah Fisk
    - 23 November 1836: Lydia Peck
    - 25 November 1836: Augustus W. Smith
    - 19 December 1836: Samuel Luckey
  - 1837
    - 1837: Prof. Stewart
    - 1837: W. C. Brown
    - 10 January 1837: La Roy Sunderland
    - 21 February 1837: Samuel Luckey
    - 8 March 1837: Samuel Luckey
    - 19 May 1837: Marcy Palmer
    - 30 August 1837: Samuel B. Buckley
    - 11 September 1837: Editors of the Christian Advocate
    - 19 September 1837: Oren Allton
    - 19 October 1837: Samuel Luckey
    - 25 October 1837: Benj. W. Britt
    - 28 October 1837: Marcia Knowlton
    - 7 December 1837: Samuel Luckey
    - 18 December 1837: Samuel Luckey
  - 1838
    - January 1838: Samuel Luckey
    - 3 January 1838: Unknown
    - 6 January 1838: Samuel Luckey
    - 8 January 1838: Charles Collins
    - 10 January 1838: Daniel Brayton
    - 15 January 1838: Charles P. Bragdon
    - 2 February 1838: Ruth P. Fisk
    - 24 February 1838: Samuel Luckey
    - 27 February 1838: Samuel Luckey
    - 1 March 1838: Samuel Luckey (Editors of the Christian Advocate)
    - 1 March 1838: Charles Collins
    - 7 March 1838: Samuel Luckey
    - 16 March 1838: Ruth P. Fisk
    - 16 March 1838: Ruth P. Fisk
    - 8 April 1838: Marcia Knowlton
    - 8 April 1838: Isaiah Fisk
    - 24 April 1838: Editors of the Christian Advocate
    - 29 May 1838: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 11 June 1838: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 18 June 1838: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
    - 13 July 1838: Samuel Luckey
    - 16 July 1838: Isaiah Fisk
    - 4 August 1838: Charles Collins
    - 15 August 1838: Mary Fisk Allton
    - 3 September 1838: Samuel Luckey
    - 10 September 1838: Samuel Luckey
    - 17 October 1838: Daniel Filmore
    - 3 December 1838: Ruth Peck (Fisk)
  - 1839
    - 7 January 1839: Samuel Luckey (Christian Advocate & Journal)
    - 24 January 1839: Samuel Luckey (Editors of the Christian Advocate)
    - 24 January 1839: Samuel Luckey